<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The stripping of Ioseph, or The crueltie of brethren to a brother In a sermon before his Maiestie at White-Hall, by Robert Wilkinson, Doctor in Diuinitie, chaplaine in ordinarie to his Maiestie, and late pastor of Saint Olaues in Southwarke. With a consolatorie epistle, to the English-East-India Companie, for their vnsufferable wrongs sustayned in Amboyna, by the Dutch there. Published and presented vnto them, by Tho. Myriell pastor of Saint Stephens in Walbrooke.</title>
            <author>Wilkinson, Robert, Dr. in Divinity.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1625</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 86 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 27 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A15387</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 25663</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S120036</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99855239</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99855239</idno>
            <idno type="VID">20720</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A15387)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 20720)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1192:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The stripping of Ioseph, or The crueltie of brethren to a brother In a sermon before his Maiestie at White-Hall, by Robert Wilkinson, Doctor in Diuinitie, chaplaine in ordinarie to his Maiestie, and late pastor of Saint Olaues in Southwarke. With a consolatorie epistle, to the English-East-India Companie, for their vnsufferable wrongs sustayned in Amboyna, by the Dutch there. Published and presented vnto them, by Tho. Myriell pastor of Saint Stephens in Walbrooke.</title>
                  <author>Wilkinson, Robert, Dr. in Divinity.</author>
                  <author>Myriell, Thomas, d. 1629. aut</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 50, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by W[illiam] S[tansby] for Hen. Holland and Geo. Gibbs, and are to be sold at the golden Flower de luce in Popes-head Alley,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1625.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Title page in red and black.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>The first leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>East India Company --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Ambon (Indonesia) --  History --  Massacre, 1624 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:20720:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:20720:1"/>
            <p>THE STRIPPING OF IOSEPH, OR The crueltie of BRETHREN to a BROTHER.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Jn a Sermon before his</hi> MAIESTIE <hi>at</hi> White-Hall, <hi>by</hi> ROBERT WILKINSON, <hi>Doctor in Diuinitie, Chaplaine in Ordinarie</hi> to his MAIESTIE, and late Paſtor of Saint OLAVES in <hi>Southwarke.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>With a Conſolatorie Epiſtle, to the <hi>Engliſh-Eaſt-India</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie, for their vnſufferable wrongs ſuſtayned in AMBOYNA, by the DVTCH there.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Publiſhed and preſented vnto them, by</hi> Tho. Myriell Paſtor of Saint STEPHENS in WALBROOKE.</p>
            <p>LONDON Printed by <hi>W. S.</hi> for <hi>Hen. Holland</hi> and <hi>Geo. Gibbs,</hi> and are to be ſold at the golden <hi>Flower de luce</hi> in Popes-head Alley. 1625.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:20720:2"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>DEVS · INDICA</head>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:20720:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT VVORSHIPFVLL <hi>M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> Maurice Abbot,</hi> Gouernour of the EAST-INDIA Companie; and to all the reſt of the <hi>Right Worſhipfull</hi> ASSISTANTS and ADVENTVRERS in that Honorable and Worthy <hi>SOCIETIE.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Worſhipfull,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Vch and ſo great hath beene and is the exorbitancie of Mans luſts and affections, ſince the wofull fall of our ſeduced Parents, that like ouer-growing &amp; ouer-crow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing<note n="*" place="margin">Affectus qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſi vbertas ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morum eſt na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turalis. Nam ſicut in ſentes ager qui eſt natura foecundus exuberat, ſic animus incultus, &amp;c. <hi>Lactànt. diui. Inſt. lib.</hi> 6. <hi>cap.</hi> 1.</note> weedes, they haue miſerably peſtered the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:20720:3"/>
ſoile of Mans ſoule. And as to other lewd enor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities and haynous irregularities they driue wretched man: ſo eſpecially to <hi>Diſcord,</hi> and <hi>Contention,</hi> euen till it breake out into fell <hi>murder</hi> and <hi>bloudſhed.</hi> This Saint <hi>Iames</hi> plainly tells vs.<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iam.</hi> 4.1.</note> 
               <hi>From whence are warres, and contentions among you? Are they not from your luſts that fight in your members?</hi> There are three of theſe luſts, which principally ſerue this way; which<note n="a" place="margin">Tres ſunt af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectus qui ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mines in om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia facinora praecipites a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gunt, &amp;c. pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pterea poetae tres furias eſſe dixerunt, <hi>Lact. Jnſt. lib.</hi> 6. <hi>c.</hi> 19.</note> 
               <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctantius</hi> ſaith, gaue occaſion to the Poets to feigne three <hi>Furies,</hi> that is, <hi>Pride, Couetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi> and <hi>Luſt;</hi> all peſtilent weedes in the garden of Mans heart, and miſerably choaking the tender plants of <hi>Peace,</hi> and <hi>Loue.</hi> Pride is like the Bramble:<note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Judg.</hi> 9.15.</note> For as that would needes tyranniſe ouer all the Trees; So <hi>Superbia,</hi> will <hi>ſuperbire,</hi> that is, <hi>ſuper alios ire,</hi> bee aboue all: and as the Bramble is good for nothing but to ſcratch, ſo Pride willing to doe nothing but contend, for,<note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pro.</hi> 13.10.</note> Onely by pride man maketh con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention, as <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith. Couetouſneſſe or inordinate loue of riches is as Thornes (that is a fighting and pricking plant too) which hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders the Seede of the<note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>Matt.</hi> 13.22.</note> Word, that it cannot grow vp to the procuring of <hi>peaee</hi> and <hi>chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie:</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:20720:3"/>
and therefore wee are commanded to cut them vp, by the Prophet,<note n="e" place="margin">
                  <hi>Jer.</hi> 4.4.</note> Breake vp your fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low ground, and ſowe not among thornes. Luſt is like a Nettle (another wrangling weede) which is called <hi>vrtica quia vrit tactu,</hi> it burnes in touching: So Concupiſcence firſt fires the body with the flame of lewd deſires, and afterwards the world with combuſtions of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord. Which being ſo noyſome, muſt by Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans be rooted vp, according to the prophecie,<note n="f" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 55.13.</note> For Thiſtles ſhall grow Firre-trees, and for Nettles the Mirtle tree. Not that wee can wholly deſtroy theſe deſires,<note n="g" place="margin">Nos affectus &amp; perturbatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, quam diu in tabernaculo corporis huius habitamus, &amp; fragili carne circundamur, moderari &amp; regere poſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, amputare non poſſumus. <hi>Hieron. ad De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metrian.</hi> Apud nos ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues ſanctae ciui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatis ſecundum Deum viuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes metuunt cupiunt<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, gaudent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que, <hi>Auguſt. de Ciuit. Dei, lib.</hi> 14. <hi>cap.</hi> 9.</note> that is neither poſsible to Man, nor required of God, but that we ſhould curbe, and reſtraine them, and turne their violence another way, bee ambitious of heauen, couetous of ſpirituall graces, and luſt after Gods preſence in grace and glorie.</p>
            <p>But alas, in ſtead of tilling the ground of our hearts, we let it lie like the ſluggards field,<note n="h" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pro.</hi> 24.30.</note> all ouer-growne with Briars and Thornes of contentious luſts, euen to ſuch an harueſt, that it may ſeeme, ſome men endeauour by crueltie and couetouſneſſe, not onely to kill humanitie and kindneſſe in their hearts, but euen to depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulate, and roote out mankinde it ſelfe from
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:20720:4"/>
the earth. This is euident and plaine by all ſtories from the beginning of the world. I will let paſſe <hi>Cain, Nimrod, Nebuchadnezzar, Pharaoh, Antiochus, Herod, Nero, Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian, Diocleſian, Decius, Maximus, Lici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius, Phalaris, Dionyſius, Sylla,</hi> and others, both becauſe they are innumerable, and would take vp a large volume to touch but a little of each, and alſo becauſe they being heathens are no better then dogs in accompt, and euery dogge will doe his kinde. Neither will I trouble you with the relation of the ſtrange perſecution vſed against the Chriſtians in the primitiue Church, which were done with as much wit, and malice, as Hell and the Deuill could deuiſe, as may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare by that which Saint <hi>Cyprian</hi> obiects to <hi>Demetrian.</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Deus ſolus in terris aut non colitur, aut non eſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pune quod co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litur. Innoxios iuſtos, Deo charos, domo priuas, patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monio ſpolias, catenis pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis, carcere includis, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtijs, gladio, ignibus punis. Nec ſaltem contentus es dolorum no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrorum com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendio, &amp; ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plici ac veloci breuitate poe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narum, admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues laniandis corporibus longa tormen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta, multiplicas lacerandis viſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceribus, nume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſa ſupplicia, nec feritas at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que immanitas tua vſitatis po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt contenta eſſe tormentis, excogitat no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uas paenas in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genioſa crude<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litas. <hi>Cyprian. ad Demetrian.</hi>
               </note> The onely true God, ſaith he, is either not worſhipped at all, or elſe not freely without puniſhment. Innocent, iuſt, and men deare in Gods ſight, doeſt thou driue out of their houſes, ſpoile them of their patrimonie, binde in chaines, ſhut vp in priſon, and tormenteſt with wilde beaſts, fire and ſword. Neither art thou contented with compendious and ſhort paines, or torments which would quickly diſpatch vs, but ſundrie engines are multiplied to teare out
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:20720:4"/>
our very bowels leiſurely, and thy ſauage diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition is not ſatisfied with vſuall tortures, but thy ſubtill crueltie hath found out new puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to deſtroy vs. But theſe wretches lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in ſhort time to ſtake their hands, whileſt they found,<note n="m" place="margin">Vigelius Saturninus qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>primus hic gla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dium in nos e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>git, lumina a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſit. Claudius Herminianus in Cappadocia indigne ferens &amp;c. Cum viuus vermibus ebul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſſet, Nemo ſciat aiebat, ne gaudeant Chriſtiani, <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tull. ad Scap. cap.</hi> 5.</note> partly vengeance falling on their owne heads for hating Gods Saints, and<note n="n" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Ariſt. Eth.</hi> 1.13. Nec ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men deficiet haec ſecta quam tunc ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis aedificari<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſcias, cum caedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>videtur. <hi>Tertul. ad Scap. cap.</hi> 5. Dum opprimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur creſcit. <hi>Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar. l</hi> 7. <hi>de Trin.</hi> Haud ſecus quam ſi quis vitem ſecatione pronocet ad vbertatem. <hi>Juſt. Martyr. Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loq cum Tryphon. &amp;c.</hi>
               </note> part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Church to increaſe, by that which they thought would deſtroy it.</p>
            <p>The more meruaile it is that Chriſtians<note n="o" place="margin">Crudelitas veſtra, gloria noſtra eſt. <hi>Tertull. ad Scapul.</hi>
               </note> whoſe glory it was to endure cruelty from the hands of others, ſhould in time through pride and couetouſneſſe come to looſe their glory by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecuting cruelty on others. For that it is ſo, I would Writers had neuer had iuſt occaſion to affirme, nor Readers iuſt reaſon to lament. Strange it is that Chriſtians I ſay,<note n="p" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.33.</note> whoſe God is the God of peace,<note n="q" place="margin">
                  <hi>Jſa.</hi> 9.6.</note> whoſe Sauiour the Prince of peace,<note n="r" place="margin">
                  <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6.15.</note> whoſe calling is to the Goſpell of peace, ſhould through ſauage crueltie giue as much offence to Heathens, as euer heretofore Heathens gaue to them. For what true religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous heart will not grieue to heare, that which is written by a Chriſtian, concerning the <hi>Perui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:20720:5"/>
a people of the Weſt <hi>Indies,</hi>
               <note n="ſ" place="margin">Poſtquam in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſis Peruſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um Hiſpanis mores eorum, facta &amp; atrocia ſaeuitiae exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pla quae paſſim ab ijs edeban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, inſpexere, nunquam ex eo non modo fateri volue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt, nos eſſe Chriſtianos fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lios Dei (ſicuti ab Hiſpanis audiebant) ſed nec ita quidem in lucem edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tos, vt vulgo naſci homines ſolent. Quippe fieri non poſſe vt tam ferox &amp; truculentum a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimal ab vllo homine geni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum, &amp; faeminae partu editum ſit. Ita<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> eorum animis penitus inſedit haec o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinio, nos mari eſſe ortos, ac proinde nos vira Cochie vocant, quíppe Cochie apud eos valet Mare, &amp; vira ſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mam ſignificat. Ergo nos è mari concretos, &amp; coalitos, ſpuma<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> nutritos, vulgo fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt, ac veniſſe in terras ad vaſtandum, &amp; perdendum mundum. <hi>Benzo. hiſt. non. orb. lib.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 21.</note> who per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuing the direfull and irefull carriage of the <hi>Spaniard</hi> towards them, did not onely refuſe to acknowledge Chriſtians to be Gods ſonnes, but alſo denyed them to bee bred and borne into the World after the common faſhion of men, thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king it could neuer be, that ſo ſauage and bloud-thirſtie Creatures could either bee begotten of Man or brought forth of Woman. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they were verily of this opinion, that theſe men were bred of the Sea, and nurſed vp of the froath of it, and afterwards ſent to Land to waſte and deſtroy Mankinde out of the world. And ſo ill did theſe pretended Conuerters carrie themſelues in that worke of planting Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie among the Heathens, that the poore <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dians</hi> openly profeſſed vnto them,<note n="t" place="margin">Poſtquam Hathney cogitabundus aliquandiu haefiſſet, à monacho petijt vtrum etiam Hiſpanis caelorum janua pateret, Cui reſpondenti bonis Hiſpanis patere, Cacicus, fine longiore deliberatione coelum ſe nolle petere, dixit, ſed potius inferos, ne eadem illi cum hac crudeli gente, manfio communis eſſet. Et his laudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus, honori buſue Deus &amp; ſancta fides ab Hiſpanis in America afficiuntur. <hi>Barthol. Caſáus. Narrat. crudel. Hiſpan. pag.</hi> 23.</note> That they had rather goe to Hell by themſelues, then to Heauen with the <hi>Spaniards.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But theſe things were done farre from home,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:20720:5"/>
a great way abroad, it may bee there is better behauiour among our ſelues. It ſhould be I am ſure. God hath ingrafted in euery mans heart ſhame and feare, and theſe<note n="u" place="margin">Omne ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum aut timore aut pudore na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tura Perfudit. <hi>Tertull. Apolog. cap.</hi> 1.</note> ſaith <hi>Tertullian,</hi> are the bridles to reſtraine the necke of cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell tyrannie and greedy auarice. But<note n="*" place="margin">Auaritia eſt hydria Samari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tanae, de quâ qui biberit ſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et iterum. <hi>Petr. Bleſenſ. Epiſt.</hi> 141.</note> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouring Couetouſneſſe, which like the <hi>Samari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans</hi>
               <note n="x" place="margin">
                  <hi>Joh.</hi> 4.28.</note> water-pot, is neuer filled, but ſtill thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth, and like a man ſicke of the Dropſie (who the more hee drinketh, the more he may) is neuer<note n="y" place="margin">Haec ſitis di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitiarum miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris pectoribus aſſidet, &amp; am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitionis ſalſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go, bibulam a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimam occu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pat, vt per fas &amp; nefas ad lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca ſuperiora, &amp;c. <hi>Cypr. de nat. Chriſt. in Prolog.</hi> Auaritia nullis expletur opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus, &amp; quanto amplius habu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erit, plus re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quirit, &amp; ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> copia ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>opia minuitur. <hi>Hieron. Epita. Paulae.</hi>
               </note> contented neither full nor faſting, breaketh through theſe brazen gates of ſhame and feare, and with her iron hands of Woluiſh rapacitie, ſeekes to ſatisfie her luſt vpon euery obiect, though thouſands and ten thouſands muſt periſh for it. Which I could make plaine by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite particulars, if it were a thing that needed any great proofe.</p>
            <p>But I will giue you but one inſtance onely, which will aboundantly ſuffice in this caſe, and that is the infinite crueltie and oppreſsion which hath beene vſed by the Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> againſt the whole Chriſtian world, for the ſatisfying of his <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ulturean auarice and Luciferian pride. What depoſing of Kings, expoſing of their Crownes, transferring their Kingdomes, ſlaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:20720:6"/>
their Subiects, demoliſhing Temples, ſac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king and ranſacking of Cities, exhauſting trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, emunging mens purſes, there haue beene by this meanes, the whole West can witneſſe, and our Anceſtors in this Kingdome as well as any.<note n="z" place="margin">Videſis lector Matth. Pariſ. de hac re miſere conquerentem.</note> I inſiſt not on particulars, for it were an infinite worke. This one ſhall ſerue for all of <hi>Hildebrand,</hi> or <hi>Helbrand,</hi> called <hi>Gregorie</hi> the ſeuenth, ruining and cruelly ouerthrowing <hi>Henry</hi> that famous but vnfortunate Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour; and all for that hee would haue main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained againſt him that which by God and by mans Law is but the Princes right.</p>
            <p>Good God!<note n="a" place="margin">Quanta au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem mala, quot bella bellorum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que diſcrimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na, inde ſubſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuta ſint, quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties miſera Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma obſeſſa, capta, vaſtata, quod papa ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per papam ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cut rex ſuper regem poſitus fuerit, taedet me morare. Denique tot mala, tot ſciſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mata, tot tam animarum quam corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum pericula, hujus tempeſtaris turbo inuoluit vt ſolus ex perſecutionis immanitate ac temporis diuturnitate ad humanae miſeriae infaelicitatem ſufficeret comproban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam. <hi>Otho. Friſing. Chron. lib.</hi> 6.36.</note> What thundring of Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munications to curſe him, what exciting of other Princes to deſtroy him, what arming of his Subiects, yea his owne Sonne to rebell againſt him, what ouerthrowing of Cities, waſting of Countries, ouerturning Churches, ſpilling mans blood, weakening of whole Chriſtendome, was there at that time! Euen enough by the iudgement of a graue Hiſtorian, to proue the common calamitie of Mankinde. But if you ſhould adde to this their other Cruelties, as their
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:20720:6"/>
manifold intruſions into that See by poyſoning their Predeceſſors, their ſchiſmes by Antipopes,<note n="b" place="margin">Erant eo tempore tres qui Pontifices haberi voleba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t <hi>Gregorius</hi> 12. <hi>Benedictus</hi> 13. &amp; <hi>Iohannes</hi> 23. nec potorat fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cile iudicari quis eorum ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus ac legiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus eſſet Pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifex, cum non deeſſent ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis doctiſſimi patroni. <hi>Bell. de Pont. Rom. lib.</hi> 4. <hi>cap.</hi> 14.</note> three at a time, no man knowing which was the true Pope, their mutuall curſing and dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning each other, their violence againſt the liues and goods of holy men, as the <hi>Dulciniſts, Wickleuiſts, Waldenſes,</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Prelatos &amp; Clerum peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus aſpernan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do, &amp;c. <hi>Chron. Chron. fol.</hi> 227. Habitus eſt Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes Hus lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gua potens &amp; mundiore vita clarus- <hi>Ibid. fol.</hi> 267.</note> 
               <hi>Huſsits,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, meerely for finding fault with their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tolerable Pride, you may iuſtly conclude, that the ſcarlet Whoore, hath iuſtified <hi>Nero</hi> and <hi>Domitian,</hi> as <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> did iuſtifie <hi>Sodome</hi> and <hi>Gomorrha.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But it is no maruell to ſee the members of a falſe Church offer violence to each other, or to the Profeſſors of the Truth. For it hath euer beene ſeene,<note n="d" place="margin">Semper &amp; boni omnia mala paſſi ſunt, &amp; fecerunt ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li. <hi>Saluian. de gubern. Dei, l.</hi> 1.</note> that good men haue ſuffered ill, and euill men inflicted it, ſaith <hi>Saluian.</hi> As for righteous men they offer no violence to any. None hurts, nor deſtroyes in all my holy Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine,<note n="e" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 11.9.</note> ſaith God.<note n="f" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 2.4.</note> There, Swords are tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned into Sythes, and Speares into Mattocks. Whilſt quite contrarie, Among falſe Chriſtians Tooles of good husbandrie, are made inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of crueltie,
<q>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>irg. Georg. lib.</hi> 1. Sarcula ceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bant, verſique in pila ligones, Factaque de raſtri pondere caſſis erat. <hi>Ouid. Faſt.</hi> 1.</note> Et curvae rigidos falces conflantur in enſes.</q>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:20720:7"/>
And crooked Sythes are turned into ſharpe-bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Swords. Religion is as jealous as Loue, it can indure no Riualitie. And therefore the greateſt hate that euer Hath beene, ſaith<note n="h" place="margin">Nihil germa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nos Dei culto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res aeque ſe conciliat, at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> conſentientes de Deo ſenten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiae; quemad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modum co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tra, nulla re faci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius diſſoluun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur amicitiae quam diuerſa in huiuſmodi tebus animoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſententia. <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zianzen. Orat.</hi> 1. <hi>de Pace.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zianzen,</hi> hath ariſen from contrary Religions; as on the other ſide, the greateſt Loue that is to be found on earth, is among them that agree to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in the Truth.</p>
            <p>But, O then, what ſhall we ſay to them who being of the ſame Religion, and vpon termes of peace, haue practiſed moſt exquiſite torments vpon the innocent bodies of their Friends and Confederates? I ſay of the ſame Religion, if there be any Religion indeed in thoſe men, who by ferine crueltie maintayne their inſatiable a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uarice. For Saint <hi>Iames</hi> tells vs,<note n="i" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iam.</hi> 3.17.</note> The wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome that is from aboue, is firſt pure, then peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, gentle, eaſie to be intreated, full of mercy, and good fruits, without iudging, and without hypocriſie. Which plainly ſhewes, that where there is not<note n="k" place="margin">Lorin. com. in Iacob. <hi>3.17.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>verbum</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the wordes and workes of peace, but of contention and violence, there is no Religion indeed. The World knowes what I meane, and your <hi>Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Societie</hi> haue vnderſtood it,<note n="l" place="margin">Bernard.</note> 
               <hi>non verbis ſed verberibus,</hi> as one ſpeaketh, by that most
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:20720:7"/>
inhumane and woluiſh butchering vp of your faithfull Seruants, and Agents, at <hi>Amboyna</hi> in the <hi>Eaſt Indies,</hi> by the moſt vnheard tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the perfidious <hi>Dutch</hi> there. Of which I may ſay as S. <hi>Auguſtin</hi> ſaid of the ciuill warres of <hi>Marius</hi> and <hi>Sylla,</hi>
               <note n="m" place="margin">Quae rabies exteraru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium, quae fae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitia Barbaro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum huic de ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uibus victoriae ciuium com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parari poteſt? <hi>Aug. de Ciuit. Dei, lib.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 29.</note> What rage of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reine Nations, what bloodſhead of Barbarians, is to be compared to this treacherous tyrannie of Confederates to their Friends?<note n="n" place="margin">Pax cum bello de cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delitate certa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uit, &amp; vicit. Illud enim pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrauir arma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tos, iſta nuda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tos. <hi>Auguſt. de Ciuit. Dei, lib.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 28.</note> Peace hath contended with Warre for crueltie, and gone beyond it, for Warre ouerthrowes armed men, but this coloured Peace hath proſtrated naked men. Naked, ſaue onely of innocency, that, their ſoules being throughly cloathed withall, hath kept them ſafe from the ſcandall of trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon laid on them, or the torments of hell threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to them.</p>
            <p>But, O vnkinde, vnnaturall! You this to vs? We this from you? Whilſt the Blood of our valiant Countrimen lies reeking on the ground, to keepe you in your owne Land, doe you waſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully ſpill the blood of our faithfull Countrimen in a ſtrange Land? O more then Scythian bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bariſme. Doe you ſo requite vs? What will you gaine by this, but in time to ſtinke before other Nations, as<note n="o" place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 34.30.</note> 
               <hi>Simeon</hi> and <hi>Leui</hi> did before
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:20720:8"/>
the <hi>Shechemites?</hi> And therefore if your ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uage hearts haue any place for patience, or if you be not vtterly forſaken of all humane inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuitie, heare the aduiſe of him that wiſhes you well.</p>
            <p>First, fall downe on your knees, and with bleeding hearts<note n="p" place="margin">Primus foe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licitatis gradus eſt non delin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quere, ſecun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus delicta a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnoſcere; Illic currit inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centia integra quae ſeruet, hic ſuccedit me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dela quae ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net. <hi>Cyp. Ep.</hi> 55.</note> confeſſe this execrable Villa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, and pray to God,<note n="q" place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 8.22.</note> that if it bee poſsible, this lewdneſſe may bee forgiuen you. For I per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue you are in the gall of bitterneſſe, and in the bond of iniquitie. Secondly, as one aduiſed a leſſe malefactor,<note n="r" place="margin">Et ſiquidem patratum eſt ſeclus, preca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, ſupplicato, obſecrato, te ad Iudicum pedes prouol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uere ne deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas, donec im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petraueris vt tradaris, ex ſententia cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culo<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> Iudicis carnifici vt ſuppliciu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> des. Honori tibi vertetur apud inferos, ante purgatum hinc ire. <hi>Syneſ. ep.</hi> 44</note> Begge and intreat ſome temporall Iudge to cenſure you, and deliuer you into the hands of ſome Executioner, to bee put to death. It will be an honour vnto you, at your future triall, to part out of this world purged by iudiciall cenſure. If it had been onely an outward iniurie in the buſineſſe of Trade and Traffike, yet were you bound in conſcience to make<note n="ſ" place="margin">Si enim res aliena propter quam peccatu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſt, cum reddi poſſit non red<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditur, non agi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur poenitentia ſed ſingitur. Si autem veraciter agitur, Non remittetur peccatum niſi reſtituatur ablatum. <hi>Auguſt. ad Maced. Epiſt.</hi> 54.</note> reſtitution by pecuniarie compenſation. For that which is vniuſtly taken and peruerſly detayned, will bee at laſt as vnpleaſing to the conſcience,<note n="t" place="margin">Poſtea implebitur os eius glacea, <hi>Pro.</hi> 20.17.</note> as is grauell in the teeth. But for murder what recompence can bee made, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:20720:8"/>
all the world is not able to reſtore life againe to the poorest creature depriued of it? And therefore Gods appointment is,<note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 9.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> that whoſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſheddeth mans blood, by man ſhall his blood bee ſhed. Making it iuſt, that each man ſhall ſuffer in himſelfe, what he hath firſt done to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other. Yea, in iniuries of a leſſe nature then Murther, <hi>Lex talionis</hi> takes place,<note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 5.38. <hi>Exod.</hi> 21.24. <hi>Leuit.</hi> 24.20. Sciendum eſt quod Deus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> lebat iſtam <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> nam inſligi, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> quilibet pate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retur malum quod fecerat. <hi>Toſt. Abulenſ. Tom.</hi> 2. <hi>in Mat. quaeſt.</hi> 322.</note> An eye for an eye, and a tooth for a tooth; for God wold haue euery man indure what he hath done. And the very Heathens thought this a moſt iuſt Law, as<note n="f" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ariſtot. Ethic. lib.</hi> 5. Dicunt Rhadaman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thum dicere, rectam fieri vindic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>am ſi quis patiatur ea quae fecit. Erat autem Rhadaman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thus Iudex ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiſſimus, &amp; propter hoc apud Gentiles Poetica fictio poſuit eum eſſe vnu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n de tribus iudicibus animarum apud inferos &amp; ſic tanquam fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſum allegat eum Ariſtoteles. <hi>Toſt. Abulenſ. in Mat. Tom.</hi> 2. <hi>quaeſt.</hi> 322.</note> 
               <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> reports of the <hi>Pythago<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reans;</hi> who further tels that euen <hi>Rhada<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manthus</hi> himſelfe could not but iudge this Law to be iust. Wherefore it is no maruell that the<note n="g" place="margin">Si mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brum rupit meum ex pacto talio eſto. <hi>Ludou. Charond. leg. Antiquar. Leg.</hi> 78.</note> 
               <hi>Romanes</hi> put it into their twelue Tables. And howſoeuer ſome ancient Jewes ſay, that in wrongs of a leſſe nature then Murther, this law was not exactly obſerued, but ſomtime for an eye or a finger, money was taken either according to common eſtimation, as<note n="h" place="margin">
                  <hi>V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i</hi> Toſtat. loc. Citat.</note> 
               <hi>Rabbi Solomon</hi> hath it, or after the will of him that endured the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iurie, as <hi>Ioſephus</hi> ſets downe; Yet for Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:20720:9"/>
there was no agreement to be made for mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, nothing could ſatisfie but the Death of the murtherer, according to Gods owne edict. <hi>Num. 35.31.</hi> Yee ſhall take no ſatisfaction for the life of a Murtherer which is guiltie of death, but he ſhall ſurely be put to Death.</p>
            <p>If you will doe none of theſe, then know that none<note n="*" place="margin">Scito quod nulla ciuitas impunelatura ſit ſanguinis noſtri effuſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem. <hi>Tertull. ad Scapul.</hi>
               </note> of your Cities or Territories ſhall drinke in our blood without iuſt Reuenge. The Heathens could ſay and confeſſe of Murthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers,<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 28.4.</note> that vengeance would not ſuffer them to liue, and that<note n="b" place="margin">Victima haud vlla am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plior poteſt magiſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> opima mactari Ioui, quam Rex ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Senec. Herc. tur.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Iupiter</hi> accounts the murthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of Tyrants, as the fattest ſacrifice. And if you feele no outward Iudgement fall vpon you, thinke not your ſelues free, or innocent, nor yet voide of puniſhment, for it is<note n="c" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſ. Epiſt. <hi>32.</hi>
               </note> torment enough to bee wicked and to be let alone in the guilt of ſinne. Yea, in the opinion of all Diuines, <hi>
                  <hi rend="sup">z</hi>
               </hi> it is the moſt miſerable thing in the world,<note n="d" place="margin">Qui per diu ſceleratus im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>punitus ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net, eum opor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tet exiſtimare infaeliciſſimum de quo neque Deus ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo ſollicitus eſt. <hi>Syneſ. Epiſt.</hi> 44. Dilatio vindictae dat locum paenitentiae. Nec dici poteſt, nulla ibi eſt vltio vbi nulla conuerſio eſt, quia mens dura &amp; ingrata jam fibi ipſa ſupplicium eſt. <hi>Leo ſer.</hi> 5. <hi>de Epiph.</hi> Hoc eſt terribile, hoc extremum, cum jam non corripimur pro peccatis, cum jam non corrigimur delinquentes. <hi>Orig. hom.</hi> 8. <hi>in Exod.</hi>
               </note> to ſinne and thriue therein, for that bringeth the ſinner to hardneſſe of heart, and ſtupiditie in his leud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, which makes him fit fewell for the euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting fire of Hell. And how much better were
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:20720:9"/>
it for a man to indure ſome chaſticement, yea to put himſelfe to paine by Repentance in this world, then to runne on in the delights of ſinne, and ſo to bee tormented with eaſeleſſe and end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe paines in Hell eternally.</p>
            <p>But you are ſecure of that, for you haue done nothing but Iuſtice, you haue puniſhed Traitors and malefactors, Such euen by their owne con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſsion, &amp;c. But O vnpoliticke crueltie! Will you ſo farre vſurpe vpon the Deuils right, that you will firſt make men guiltie; and then plague them for it. Can you bee ſo ignorant of the law of Nature and Nations, as not to know, that<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Confeſſio fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cta in tormen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis non valet.</hi> ff. de quaeſt. lib. <hi>1. §</hi> Diuus. Bart. Pum. Summ. in verbo Confeſſio.</note> Confeſsion forced from a man by tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, is of no value againſt him. The Law ſaith that no torment ſhould bee vſed,<note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Tortura ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicijs non prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cede<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tibus infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renda non eſt.</hi> Panorm. in cap. Cum in contem. de reg. iur. Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thol. Fum. Sum. in verb. Tortur.</note> without ſome probabilities before cauſing ſuſpition in the partie tormented:<note n="c" place="margin">Confeſſio fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cta in tortura, ſi non perſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret non praejudicat, quare videtur feciſſe metu tormentorum. <hi>Panormit. in lib.</hi> 1. <hi>H. de quaeſt. cap.</hi> 1. <hi>&amp;</hi> 31. <hi>queſt.</hi> 2. <hi>Lotarius.</hi>
               </note> and that if a man con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe in torments and denie it afterwards, ſuch confeſsion is nothing, as proceeding from feare of torments. Now that this was the caſe of our innocent Countrey-men, <hi>viz.</hi> To bee accuſed without proofe, or probabilitie, yea to bee for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced by torments to accuſe themſelues, which
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:20720:10"/>
they afterwards vpon their Deaths ſtiffely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyed, is ſo cleere and plaine, that no mire and dirt of contrary aſperſion and accuſation can obſcure it, or deface it; and hath beene ſo ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently in two Treatiſes proued vnto you, that all the water betweene <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Amboy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na,</hi> cannot waſh you cleane from the crimes of treacherous Crueltie, and cruell Treacherie.</p>
            <p>But to leaue theſe men, let me in few words ſpeake to <hi>you, O worthy and noble Aduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turers.</hi> It cannot chuſe but bee a great griefe vnto you, as it is to euery true Engliſh heart,<note n="d" place="margin">Difficile eſt preſſam malis innocentiam non dolere. <hi>Hieron. ad Iuli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anum.</hi>
               </note> to ſee innocencie and fidelitie ſuffer what is due to fraud and villanie. Yet this, God often permits, for reaſon beſt knowne to himſelfe. In ſuch caſes, wee are with<note n="e" place="margin">
                  <hi>Leuit.</hi> 10.3.</note> 
               <hi>Aaron</hi> to lay the hand on the mouth, and to bee patient, which is the onely<note n="f" place="margin">Sudatur e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nim ac labora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur quamdiu hic viuitur; Nec ſud anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus &amp; laboran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibus alia poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſunt quam pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tientiae ſubue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nire ſolatia. <hi>Cypr. de bono pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient.</hi>
               </note> comfort in all diſtreſſes. This is that vertue which keepes a man in<note n="g" place="margin">
                  <hi>Luc.</hi> 21.19.</note> poſſeſsion of himſelfe, euen when hee is vniuſtly diſpoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed of his goods. And let vs not wonder that we muſt bee patient in bearing wrongs from one another, for God is ſo himſelfe toward vs, who wrong him continuallie;<note n="h" place="margin">Quotidie contumelia afficitur praeſens, &amp; audiens &amp; videns, &amp; ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> fulmen immi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit, ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> mare juſſit terram inundare, &amp;c. <hi>Chryſoſt. hom.</hi> 3. <hi>ad Po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Antioch.</hi>
               </note> And though hee
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:20720:10"/>
bee able to reuenge himſelfe to the full, yet hee forbeares it with infinite long animitie. Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der againe, that Chriſtian warfare differs from the<note n="*" place="margin">In Olympi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis illis certa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minibus, co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronem conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quuntut qui decertant; At in Chriſti pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laeſtra contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria coronarum lex eſt. Sic e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nim lege ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citum eſt, vt qui percutitur, non qui percu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tit, &amp;c. <hi>Iſid. Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſ. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 196.</note> Olympian combatings, for there, hee which ſtrake the greateſt blow went away with the garland; but here, not hee which ſtrikes, but hee which beares the greateſt ſtroke ſhall goe away with the Crowne. Adde vnto this, that God is the<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <p>Plus impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bum illum cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dis ſuſtinendo: ab illo enim vapulabit, cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ius gratia ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtines. <hi>Tert. de Patientia.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Patientes facit de ſecutura vl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione ſecuritas <hi>Cypr. ad Demet.</hi>
                  </p>
               </note> Reuenger of the Innocent, and the ſeuere Puniſher of ſuch as offer iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries to their Brethren. For hee who hath ſaid,<note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.35. <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.19.</note> 
               <hi>Vindicta mihi,</hi> Vengeance is mine, hath alſo ſaid, <hi>Ego rependam,</hi> I will duly ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it. Neither feare you, but that this late inhumane Practiſe in <hi>Amboyna</hi> is regiſtred in Gods blacke Booke to bee repaid againe vnto the Actors, with full meaſure in due time. In the meane ſeaſon, let vs not ceaſe to waite vpon God, and commit our cauſe vnto him, comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting our ſelues thus farre, that yet it is much more<note n="c" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Jſid. Pel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſ. lib. <hi>2.</hi> Epiſt. <hi>257.</hi>
               </note> wretched a thing to doe iniurie our ſelues, then to ſuffer it from others.</p>
            <p>Which that <hi>You</hi> may the better doe, I haue preſumed to offer vnto your Worſhipfull Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance, this <hi>excellent enſuing Cordiall,</hi>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:20720:11"/>
preſcribed, and tempered by a moſt skilfull <hi>Doctor.</hi> And if you pleaſe, let <hi>It</hi> bee as<note n="n" place="margin">1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 16.23.</note> 
               <hi>Dauids</hi> Harpe to <hi>Saul,</hi> a peece of ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall melodie, to expell from you that diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bance of minde, which the euill ſpirit of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſtice, and ambitious Auarice in <hi>thoſe falſe Friends,</hi> hath offered to bring vpon you. It hath long lyen by mee, wayting for ſome occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to come abroad, and would God it had wanted this at this time. But ſeeing it is as it is, I beſeech you to accept it, and reade it, and J doubt not, but as you ſhall finde in <hi>Ioſephs</hi> brethren enuie and malice to bee an old diſeaſe; ſo you ſhall alſo finde in <hi>Ioſeph</hi> himſelfe,<note n="a" place="margin">Patientia quae eſt inſide oſſa ſunt inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius, ipſa ſunt quae frangi no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> poſſunt. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 34.20. <hi>Auguſt. in Pſal.</hi> 33.</note> patience and dependance vpon God an ancient Antidote. I muſt confeſſe for my ſelfe, J haue beene much pleaſed and deligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in reading of it, as once the <hi>royall</hi> and <hi>noble Auditorie</hi> was affected in hearing of it, and therefore I am the more willing to commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate to others, what I haue found beneficiall to my ſelfe. The rather, for that I am much bound to your Worſhips for many charitable fauours receiued from you, for all which I haue returned or can returne nothing but my poore
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:20720:11"/>
Prayers to <hi>GOD</hi> for your proſperous and flouriſhing eſtate, and happie ſucceſſe in your moſt Honourable though hazardous and dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous Enterprizes. And theſe (my prayers I meane) which are the<note n="p" place="margin">Aduerſus ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma, milites, Gothos quo<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> lachrymae meae armaſunt. Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia enim imuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menta ſunt ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerdotis. <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſ. in Auxent. Orat.</hi> 5. <hi>Tom.</hi> 3.</note> weapons of a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Miniſter, ſhall neuer bee layd downe whileſt breath is in my bodie, but I will<note n="q" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.30. Vim facimus Deo non com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pellendo ſed flendo, &amp;c. <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſ.</hi>
               </note> ſtriue thereby euen with <hi>GOD</hi> himſelfe, and againſt all your Enemies, that you may ſtill long proſper in your great and weightie Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires of Trade, to the glory of <hi>GOD,</hi> the honour of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation, the inriching of our Weale-publike, the comfort and content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of your owne hearts, and finally the ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall locupletation of the poore Heathens, with the treaſurie of the <hi>knowledge</hi> of <hi>CHRIST,</hi> one <hi>dram</hi> whereof is more worth, then all the Wealth of the world beſide. And indeed, this is one principall end of Merchandizing, if not in Mans purpoſe, yet in the intention and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment of <hi>GOD.</hi> For
<q>—<note n="r" place="margin">Virgil.</note> Non omnis fert omnia tellus.</q>
ſaith the Poet, Euerie Land abounds not with euery Commoditie,<note n="ſ" place="margin">— Nonne vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des croceos vt Tmolus odo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, India mit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titebur mol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les ſua thura Sabei? At Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lybes nudi fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum. <hi>Virgil.</hi>
               </note> But one Countrey is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:20720:12"/>
for one thing, and another for ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. <hi>Seneca</hi> could ſee no other end of this, but that<note n="t" place="margin">Vt neceſſari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um mortalibus eſſet inter ſe ipſos commer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cium, ſi inui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cem alius ab alio aliquis pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teret. <hi>Senec. Epiſt.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>GOD</hi> would neceſsitate men to a kinde of familiaritie with each other, whileſt one was conſtrained to ſupplie his wants by another. But the maine reaſon is, that the glorious merchandiſe of his Holy <hi>GOSPELL</hi> might alſo bee communicated to <hi>THEM</hi> that want it, and ſo whileſt men ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenture for Earth they might gaine Heauen. Which I feare me hath beene rather hinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red then furthered by <hi>theſe vnciuill broyles,</hi> and <hi>vnconſcionable proceedings</hi> of Thoſe that would make the world beleeue <hi>they</hi> are the onely <hi>deuout maintainers</hi> of <hi>RELIGION;</hi> concerning <hi>whom</hi> I would haue ſaid much more, but that I am reſtrayned by that ſpeach of the Orator, which<note n="u" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Jſid. Pelaſ-epiſt. lib. <hi>2.</hi> Ep. <hi>163.</hi>
               </note> one commends as a Patterne to bee followed, I feare leaſt if I ſhould ſpeake that which befits <hi>them</hi> to heare, J ſhould fall into that language which becomes not mee to vtter. So leauing <hi>them</hi> to <hi>GODS</hi> cenſure, I humbly take my leaue of your Worſhips, beſeeching the <hi>GOD</hi> of Heauen to looke vpon <hi>You</hi> with the fauourable eye of his all-ſufficient
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:20720:12"/>
Prouidence, that by his heauenly Bleſsing vpon your painefull proceedings, You may all become profitable Members of his <hi>CHVRCH</hi> in this world, and glorious <hi>SAINTS</hi> in his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome in the world to come; and this for <hi>CHRIST</hi> his ſake, To whom with the Father and the holy Ghoſt, one <hi>GOD</hi> in ſubſtance, three Perſons in ſubſiſtence, bee all honour and glorie, now and for euer, <hi>AMEN.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>From my Study.</hi> 
                  <date>Feb. <hi>1. 1625.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Your Worſhips: in all the Seruices of Loue and Dutie: <hi>THO: MYRIELL.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:20720:13"/>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:20720:13"/>
            <head>THE STRIPPING OF IOSEPH.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>GEN. 37.23.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Now when <hi>IOSEPH</hi> was come vnto his brethren, they ſtript <hi>IOSEPH</hi> out of his Coate, euen the party-coloured Coate which was vpon him.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Scripture which I haue read, is part of a tragicall hiſtorie made famous to the Church, by executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of an infamous and horrible fact, wherein we haue ten againſt one, men a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt a childe, all brethren againſt a naturall brother, making a moſt wicked and bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:20720:14"/>
aſſault; a ſinne in all circumſtances (Chriſts death excepted) not in the world to bee matched againe. The report of it ſtandeth briefly thus; <hi>Iacob</hi> the father of theſe diſagreeing children, had (as all men know) twelue ſonnes, concerning whom it befell him (as in his flocke to haue ſome white, ſome ſpotted ſheepe) ſo in his familie to haue ſome good, ſome wicked children. In this varietie wee finde that hee loued <hi>Ioſeph</hi> more then all the reſt of his children, which was partly for the loue he bare to <hi>Rachel</hi> his dead mother (a part of a kinde husband ſure, to loue his wife euen when ſhee was dead) and partly, for that <hi>Ioſeph</hi> by her death was motherleſſe; and it is a vertue doubtleſſe heroicall and princely, to defend and cheriſh the fatherleſſe and motherleſſe, widdowes and orphanes. But it is expreſſed in the Text, that hee loued <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> becauſe hee begat him in his old age; for that children ſo begotten, make the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers flouriſh, and as it were to ſeeme young a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine. But howſoeuer his father loued him intire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, ſure it is, his brethren hated him deadly. For to be beloued of all men, or to pleaſe all, is a gift yet neuer granted to any, no God himſelfe can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not obtaine it. The cauſes of their hatred may be coniectured many: either for that hee and they were borne of diuers mothers, and moſt common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, moſt mortall is the hate when the mothers breede the quarrell, and bloudie are the battels where women fight the field; Or whether they hated him, for complayning of them, as it is <hi>Ver.</hi> 2.
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:20720:14"/>
Or whether for the loue which his father bare him, as it is <hi>Verſ.</hi> 4. Or whether for his dreames, as it it <hi>Verſ.</hi> 5. Whether for any, or for all theſe cauſes, ſure it is they hated him, and ſo hated him, as they ſought for nothing but opportunitie to hurt him. In the end (as the Deuill would haue it) an opportunitie is offered. For they being in the field, <hi>Iacob</hi> ſendeth <hi>Ioſeph</hi> amongſt them, ſo that now they haue it as they would, for their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther whom they feared is out of ſight, their bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther whom they hated is in their hands. A ſhort tale to make poore <hi>Ioſeph</hi> comming towards them; firſt they ſpie him, then they conſpire a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, and vpon the meeting lay hands on him. <hi>Now when Ioſeph &amp;c.</hi> and ſo wee come to the Text; Of which that I may ſpeake to Gods glorie, and the good of this great and royall aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly, I beſeech you to aſſiſt mee with your prayers, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>I am not altogether ignorant how allegorically the Fathers haue directed the application of this ſtorie to Chriſt and his Paſſion, which in no part, or perſon in Scripture is more eminently figured then in <hi>Ioſeph.</hi> For Chriſt was beloued of God his Father in <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> hee was hated of the Iewes his brethren in <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> hee was mocked in <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> hee was ſtripped in <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> he was ſold in <hi>Ioſeph;</hi> and in the end hee was exalted in <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> and made great Lord of an euerlaſting Kingdome. Yet for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſmuch as it is not poſſible in the period and ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacitie of one houre, to ſay whatſoeuer might bee
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:20720:15"/>
ſaid, I will therefore paſſe ouer all this, and follow onely the hiſtoricall ſenſe, and make application as beſt may befit the morall vſe of life. To which purpoſe I obſerue in the Text two things, firſt, The kindneſſe of <hi>Ioſeph</hi> vnto his brethren. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, The vnkindneſſe of his brethren to him. <hi>Ioſephs</hi> kindneſſe appeareth in his comming to them and viſiting them. Their vnkindneſſe ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth in their ſtripping of him and ſpoiling him. Two worthy conſiderations, I beſeech you take notice of them, for by doing good and ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring euill, both Prince and People muſt goe to heauen.</p>
            <p>But becauſe <hi>Ioſephs</hi> kindneſſe is not here prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally mentioned, but onely to extend by cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtance the offence of his brethren, I doe make therefore that their offence, the ſubiect of my diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, and obſerue therein two things: firſt, The circumſtances of the fact. Secondly, The fact it ſelfe. The circumſtances are in number two one, of the time <hi>When, Now when Ioſeph was come vnto his brethren.</hi> The other of the <hi>Perſons,</hi> actors in the tragedie, which are all brethren. A new <hi>Thye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes</hi> and <hi>Atreus</hi> on the ſtage.</p>
            <p>For the time <hi>When,</hi> wee muſt conſider that <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cobs</hi> ſonnes were now in the field keeping ſheepe; For <hi>Iacob</hi> was alreadie rich, and knew that his ſonnes after him ſhould bee inheritors of a great land, euen the land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> yet hee ſent them not to <hi>Pharaohs</hi> Court to learne Complements, and to ioyne ciuilitie to their other abilities, and
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:20720:15"/>
ſo to make them (as many be). Gentlemen before their time; but <hi>Iacob</hi> was a plaine man, and tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted in the promiſes of God, and therfore brought vp his ſonnes to keepe ſheepe; whereas now, hee that is worth but a flocke of ſheepe, yet holds it high diſparagement to make his ſonne a ſheep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard, but makes him either a Lawyer or a Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tier ſtreight. Againe, we muſt conſider, that as it is <hi>Verſ.</hi> 12. <hi>Iacobs</hi> ſonnes were now keeping ſheep in <hi>Shechem,</hi> euen there where not long before they had committed horrible murder, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Iacob</hi> happily fearing (as fathers are euer fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full of their children) leſt for that murder, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what might be for reuenge intended, ſendeth one to ſee them. And whom doeth hee ſend? Surely, no ſeruant, but euen his beloued <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> to trie (as it is thought) if by his kindneſſe his brethren would be reconciled vnto him. But they aſſoone as they ſaw him, in ſtead of embracing him offer violence vnto him, and therefore if it bee true which is ſaid, Foule circumſtances make foule ſinnes, this was ſurely a time of all times peruerſly picked, then to execute their malice, when ſo much loue was deſerued. It is a kindneſſe ſure, but to inquire <hi>de aliorum ſalute,</hi> how other men doe; For who cares not how ill it goes with other, ſo it goe well with our ſelues? But <hi>Ioſeph</hi> did more then inquire: for hee went out to ſee how his brethren did, a ſtep beyond common friendſhip, for, <hi>Haile Maſter,</hi> and <hi>How doe you,</hi> to ſpeake friendly are e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery mans money, but hee is a friend indeed that
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:20720:16"/>
goes out at doores to doe his brother good. But whether went <hi>Ioſeph</hi> to ſeeke his brethren? Hee went into the wilderneſſe. The merit is yet more. To ſeeke men is ſubiect to errour and wandring. <hi>Ioſeph</hi> loſt himſelfe whilſt he ſought his brethren, <hi>Verſ.</hi> 15. To ſeeke men in the wilderneſſe is oft dangerous and ill betiding, <hi>Iacob</hi> thought a wild beaſt had deuoured <hi>Ioſeph;</hi> and ſo it was indeed, but a wilder beaſt then <hi>Iacob</hi> thought of. Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally it is an euill occupation to ſeeke men, Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and Magiſtrates know it who ſeeke men for ciuill obedience, and conformitie; Prelates and true Church-men know it, who ſeeke men to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion and pietie; and were it not for reſpect to God, who had not rather bee a Plough-man then a Prieſt to the people. And generally whatſoeuer good, in whatſoeuer kinde wee doe, wee muſt nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther looke for reward nor thankes at mens hands, no not when wee feede the hungrie, cloathe the naked, releeue the ſicke, and viſit (as <hi>Ioſeph</hi> did) them that haue need of viſiting. And yet we muſt take this withall, though wee doe good, and for good receiue euill againe, yet we muſt not ſo giue ouer, but for euill doe good againe, and that not as Saint <hi>Peter</hi> ſaid to Chriſt, <hi>till ſeuen times;</hi> but as Chriſt ſaid to Saint <hi>Peter, till ſeuentie times ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen times;</hi> referring euermore the ſucceſſe to God, who ſhall puniſh vnthankfulneſſe as he puniſheth the Deuill. For there be, they ſay, foure wayes of reſtoring: firſt, Good for good. Secondly, Euill for euill. Thirdly, Good for euill. Fourthly, Euill
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:20720:16"/>
for good. Hee that returneth good for good is a man, for that is humanitie to returne one kindnes for another. Hee that returneth euill for euill is a beaſt, for that is horſe play to ſtrike at him that ſtrikes at vs. He that reſtoreth good for euill is an Angell, for that exceedeth the patience of man. He that returneth euill for good is the Deuil him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and as <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith, <hi>Pro.</hi> 17.13. <hi>Euill ſhall not depart from that mans houſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond circumſtance is of the <hi>Perſons,</hi> which are <hi>Ioſeph</hi> and his brethren; <hi>Now when Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph was come to his brethren, they ſtript Ioſeph.</hi> Where we haue the firſt <hi>Ioſeph</hi> an Agent, and his brethren Patients; but the ſecond <hi>Ioſeph</hi> a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient, and his brethren Agents. For <hi>Ioſeph</hi> (though it ſeemeth ſomewhat harſh) is here twiſe called <hi>Ioſeph, Ioſeph came vnto his brethren, and, They ſtripped Ioſeph;</hi> ſo as <hi>Ioſeph</hi> when hee came vnto his brethren was <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> and now in the hands of his brethren was <hi>Ioſeph</hi> ſtill; <hi>Ioſeph</hi> in action, and in paſſion <hi>Ioſeph;</hi> that is <hi>Ioſeph</hi> when he did well, and <hi>Ioſeph</hi> when he ſuffered ill, to ſhew that no af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction or chance, can charge or peruert the Saints of God. But <hi>Ioſephs</hi> brethren are not as <hi>Ioſeph</hi> twiſe called Brethren, but firſt, <hi>Ioſeph</hi> came vnto his brethren and then not as brethren, but as meere ſtrangers onely, <hi>They, They ſtript him of his coate.</hi> So that as <hi>Ruben</hi> by inceſt loſt his birth-right, <hi>Gen.</hi> 49.4. <hi>Thy dignitie is gone,</hi> ſaith <hi>Iacob.</hi> So theſe men by their crueltie loſt their fraterni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie; Their brotherhood is gone: and therefore he
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:20720:17"/>
which found <hi>Ioſeph</hi> wandring in the Wilderneſſe told him, that his Brethren were gone away <hi>Verſ.</hi> 17. The <hi>Iewes</hi> make it myſticall and bring him in ſaying, <hi>Thy brethren are gone home,</hi> that is, <hi>Thy brethren haue forſaken brother-hood.</hi> And indeed <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph</hi> had it by Inheritance to bee forſaken, and hated of his owne Brethren, for ſo was <hi>Iacob</hi> of his Brother <hi>Eſau,</hi> and ſo was <hi>Iſaac</hi> his Grandfather of <hi>Iſmael,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.3.</note> and the dayes are come whereof the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ſpake, that <hi>Men ſhall be proud, couetous, without naturall affection.</hi> And the dayes are come, whereof CHRIST ſpake,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 10.21.</note> 
               <hi>The brother ſhall betray the bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to Death.</hi> So as CHRIST ſaid in that Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, <hi>Cauete ab hominibus, Beware of men,</hi> wee may ſtep further, and ſay, <hi>Cauete a fratribus, Beware and take heed of your owne Brethren.</hi> For there is not in the world ſo immortall and implacable hate, as the hate of Brethren. O what ſhall <hi>Pater noſter</hi> ſay, when he commeth to reckon for this!</p>
            <p>But whither ſhall a man goe in peace if not to his owne Brethren. <hi>Let there bee no ſtrife betweene thee and me</hi> (ſaith <hi>Abraham</hi> to <hi>Lot</hi>) Gen. 13.8. <hi>for wee are brethren.</hi> Which what a weight it had <hi>Moſes</hi> ſheweth, <hi>Verſ.</hi> 7. where he ſaith that the <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naanites</hi> dwelt at that time in the Land. For will not <hi>Canaanites</hi> clap their hands at this, to ſee ſuch a rent or ſchiſme in <hi>Abrahams</hi> houſe? Indeed when <hi>Niniuites</hi> oppoſe, and <hi>Canaanites</hi> kill one another, theſe goe for Dogges, and euery Dog will doe his kinde. But when <hi>Iacobs</hi> ſonnes, the ſeed of the Church, the light of the World, ſhall rob and
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:20720:17"/>
ſpoyle one another, when wee of the refined Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, the quinteſſence of Chriſtianitie, ſhall doe that oppreſſion, which they ſcorne to doe whom we ſcorne to bee like; to ſpeake plaine Engliſh, when Proteſtants fall out among themſelues, and endeuour to vndoe the good works which Papiſts haue done, wee are at a ſtand like <hi>Ioſuah</hi> at the ſiege of <hi>Ai, Ioſ.</hi> 7.8. <hi>What ſhall wee ſay when Iſrael turne their backes vpon their enemies?</hi> For as an ill man is the worſt of all Creatures, ſo an ill Chriſtian is the worſt of all men, and an ill Proteſtant is the worſt of all Chriſtians, and there is no ſinne like the ſinne of <hi>Ioſephs</hi> brethren. But as blinde <hi>Iſaac</hi> tooke <hi>Iacob</hi> for <hi>Eſau,</hi> ſo <hi>Ioſeph</hi> tooke them to bee his Brethren, who vpon tryall proued his Executio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, and his Hangmen, like the Oxe who thinkes hee goeth in a greene paſture, and then falleth into the ſlaughter. Therefore as in <hi>Luk.</hi> 10.29. a Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yer asked of <hi>Christ, Who is my neighbour?</hi> So wee had need of a Lawyer to make a new motion, and to aske of the ſame Iudge, <hi>Who is my brother.</hi> For as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>Hee is not a Iew which is one out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, but hee is a Iew which is one within.</hi> Rom. 2.28. So, he is not a Brother who hath it by name, but hee is a Brother who ſhewes it in nature. And as Saint <hi>Iames</hi> ſaith of Faith, <hi>Shew me thy Faith by thy workes.</hi> Iam. 2.18. So Brotherhood muſt be ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by brotherly workes. In truth the brother<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood that is now adayes, is but <hi>Vox artis, Wits in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument, a word of Art,</hi> and therefore in no predi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cament. The brotherhood that is now, hath theſe
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:20720:18"/>
markes, a ſmiling face, a courtly courteſie, a po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puler voyce, words faire and glorious, with a ſalu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation more then ſuperſtitious, <hi>Mary, Aurum &amp; algentum non eſt mihi.</hi> Act. 3.6. The brotherhood that is now, hath theſe flaſhes or lightnings, I am right ſorie for you, and I would it were better with you, I waite but opportunitie, I wiſh no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger life then to expreſſe my loue to you. But when you come to the matter, you muſt haue it as it is <hi>Prou.</hi> 3.28. with a <hi>Cras redi,</hi> I am at your Seruice in any other matter then this, at another time; but for this my word is paſt, you muſt come a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine to Morrow, and our diueliſh tongues are typt with <hi>Italianiſme.</hi> This is <hi>Fratrizare,</hi> but here is no Fraternitie.</p>
            <p>But now for <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> the Patient in this cruelty, <hi>Talia cur talis!</hi> That one ſo harmeleſſe, ſhould ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer ſo much harme! and that innocent men are e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery where marked out to miſery! At this, the Saints of God haue oft times not maruailed, but ſtood amazed. But maruaile not at it. The doores of the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> were all beſprinckled with blood. Affliction and ſorrow are the workes of the beſt men: and as Saint <hi>Gregorie</hi> ſaith, <hi>Licet occultum ſit, cum bonis malè euenit, &amp; malis bene, &amp;c. Though it bee a ſecret worke of</hi> GOD, <hi>when good men ſuffer Affliction and ill men Proſper, yet it is more ſecret and</hi> GOD <hi>worketh more againſt courſe and kinde, when ill men are afflicted and good men proſper.</hi> And <hi>Euſebius</hi> ſaith well to comfort in ſuch a caſe, <hi>O qui Sancto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum labores reſpicis, cur non &amp; remunerationes? O thou
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:20720:18"/>
that ſeeſt the preſent ſorrow of the Saints, why doest thou not looke vp to ſee the future ioyes of the Saints. Multi vident punctiones, ſed non vident vnctiones, Many ſee their Croſſes, but they feele not their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts.</hi> Yee ſtumble to behold the innocent <hi>Ioſeph</hi> in affliction, why behold yee not in <hi>Aegypt</hi> his glory and exaltation? Indeed the world broa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth her beſt Wine firſt, but of CHRIST it is ſaid, <hi>Tu ſeruâ ſit bonum vinum vſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> nunc.</hi> Ioh. 2.10. And <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith of the vertuous Woman, that <hi>in her latter end ſhee ſhall reioyce.</hi> Prou. 31.25.</p>
            <p>But let vs leaue the perſons and come to the fact it ſelfe. Wherein is to bee conſidered, Firſt, the manner of it, <hi>Stripping,</hi> Secondly, the prey or boo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie which they tooke from him, <hi>His coate, euen the partie-coloured Coat that was vpon him.</hi> For the firſt, <hi>Stripping</hi> is a kinde of ſhrift, not ghoſtly from ſinne, but a bodily abſoluing of men from their encombrances, as <hi>Dionyſius</hi> ſtript off the Golden coate from <hi>Iupiter,</hi> becauſe it was too heauy and cold; and the <hi>Infidels</hi> in the Old time ſpoyled the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> of their Goods, affirming it was good for them to be poore, that ſo they might goe to Heauen without hinderance. But ſurely, it had beene more ſutable, if <hi>Ioſeph</hi> comming as a meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenger from their Father, theſe men had with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence ſaluted him, for Ambaſſadours are enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayned Princely for their Princes ſake, and a good Sonne beholdeth with reuerence euen the dead
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:20720:19"/>
Picture of his Father. But here is no one of them regardeth him as comming from their Father, nay heere is no one of them who once openeth his mouth, to aske or inquire of the health and wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare of their Father, but enuy to their Brother makes them cleane forget they had a Father, and like rauening Beaſts, they runne at once vpon him. Wherein beſides their lacke of Humanitie, they are likewiſe touched with lacke of wit, to carry their miſchiefe cleanely. They might haue ſpiced their Brother a Drinke and ſent him home, I meane to his long home; but Poyſoning it ſhould ſeeme was not then in vſe. And therefore they fall to play the Lyons, not a ſhamed to hurt their Brother forceably. And indeed it is a princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in <hi>Machiauels</hi> Diuinitie, that when the Foxes skinne will not ſerue, wee may piece it out with the Lyons. But hee that hurteth his Brother ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretly, is either afraid of ſomething, or aſhamed of ſomething; but hee that wrongeth his Brother forceably, as the Prophet <hi>Micha</hi> ſpeaketh, <hi>Mich.</hi> 2.1. <hi>Becauſe his hand hath power,</hi> he doth it freely, becauſe he can do it eaſily; It ſeemeth God hath taken from him both ſhame and feare, that hee hath caſt the raynes in his necke, that he might runne to the Deuill without reſiſtance. And in truth theſe men were of a ſcandalous occupation, for when <hi>Phara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oh</hi> asked of them their Trade or Occupation, they ſaid they were Shepheards. <hi>Thy Seruants are Shepheards.</hi> Gen. 47.3. Vngentle Heardſmen of ſo
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:20720:19"/>
gentle a Beaſt. They were Shepheards indeed, but not as CHRIST ſaid of himſelfe, <hi>Ego ſum Paſtor ille bonus.</hi> Ioh. 10.11. They were farre from good Shepheards. They had ſomewhat of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel,</hi> for they kept Sheepe well; but they had ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what of <hi>Cain</hi> too, for they made little conſcience to kill their Brother. And though Stripping or Sheering were a part of their occupation, being Shepheards, yet I will not ſay, it was long of their occupation. But in truth Shepheards and Sheep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maiſters are growne cruell men of late, for they throw downe Townes and Townſhips, Houſes and Churches, they ſtrip men out of their Houſes, yea out of their Coates, and put out Men (Gods owne image) to bring in Sheepe. <hi>Nero, Diocleſian,</hi> deſtroyed but men, but theſe men deſtroy <hi>Huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num genus, Mankinde it ſelfe.</hi> Now ſurely if ſuch bee let alone, Shepheards will ſhortly bee more abhominable to <hi>Engliſh</hi> Chriſtians, then euer they were to the <hi>Aegyptians.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to come to the matter. <hi>Ioſeph</hi> ſuſtayned in this conflict foure kindes of afflictions. For, firſt, they mocke him: ſecondly, they ſtrip him: thirdly, they hazard his life: fourthly, in the end they ſold him: in all which hee was a famous fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure of Chriſt. Now hee that kills a man doeth him leſſe harme, then he that ſtrips him or ſpoiles him, for hee that killeth him makes an end of his miſerie at once, but hee that robbeth and ſpoileth and maketh him pine, he giueth him his life in pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:20720:20"/>
which is worſe then death. And hee ſaith in effect, as <hi>Saul</hi> to <hi>Dauid, Goe and ſerue other gods,</hi> that is, aſmuch as in him lyeth, he driueth him to make ſhipwrack of Conſcience, Religion, Saluation, and All. And there is no crueltie like that, to practiſe to bee rich, by wringing ſmall matters from the Poore. And therefore whereas in the Law theft was not death, it ſhould ſeeme to bee meant of poore hungrie Theeues, ſuch as <hi>Solomon</hi> ſpeaketh of, <hi>Prouerb.</hi> 6.30. Which ſteale through ſtrong neceſſitie: for when <hi>Dauid</hi> heard of a rich Thiefe that had ſtollen a poore mans ſheepe, there was no way with him, but, <hi>Hic vir mortis filius.</hi> 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 12.5. <hi>This man ſhall die the death.</hi> And great reaſon; for one rich Thiefe makes a great many poore Theeues; as in the Goſpell, one foule Spirit, one Deuill brought in ſeuen other. And therefore great reaſon the rich ſhould bee puniſhed for the poore, as they that haue giuen occaſion of ſinne to other. O there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore take heede of ſtripping, take heede of oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, <hi>He that gathereth riches wrongfully, ſhall leaue them,</hi> ſaith <hi>Ierem.</hi> 17.11. <hi>in the midst of his dayes.</hi> A memorable leſſon for great and wealthy men. It oftimes comes to paſſe that great and honorable Houſes are ſtrangely and ſuddenly made deſolate, by a cauſe not conſidered of in the World, but ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret in God, and that is, for ſome oppreſſion, either in the Father, in the Sonne, or in the Grand fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: for, <hi>Nullum tempus occurrit Deo; It is all one
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:20720:20"/>
to God.</hi> But when they build, as <hi>Geneſ.</hi> 11.3. with bricks in ſtead of ſtone, and ſlime in ſtead of mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, that is, by indirect and vnmercifull meanes, God himſelfe will giue that Houſe a name, and call it <hi>Babel,</hi> a Caſtle of confuſion. Therefore be ſure yee get your wealth by warrantable meanes, for if yee ſtrip poore <hi>Ioſeph, Ioſeph</hi> will crie, and that crie ſhall enter in at the eares of the Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and then looke what yee haue gotten, a ſecret Worme ſhall fire and conſume it. Either your ſelues ſhall liue to ſee it pull'd out of your teeth by an higher, or mightier tyrannie, or your ſonnes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> waſte it with riot and prodigalitie, or ſome <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> poſteritie ſhall forfeit it by ſome treaſon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, but yee ſhall finde it true which is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gaudet tertius haeres; Three whole Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> neuer inioy it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> which they tooke from <hi>Ioſeph</hi> was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> conſidered firſt, barely as a garment, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> him of his Coate;</hi> and then ſecondly, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>nament: <hi>Euen the party-coloured Coat that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> upon him. They ſtripped him of his Coate,</hi> they tooke not from him gold or ſiluer, as <hi>Exod.</hi> 12. the <hi>Iewes</hi> did from the <hi>Egyptians,</hi> for gold and ſiluer were not then deſired, nor yet adored as they bee now, but they tooke away his garment. Neither did they take from him a cloake or a looſe gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as in the next Chapter, <hi>Thamar</hi> ranne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way with <hi>Iudahs</hi> cloake. Much in our attire han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth looſe about vs; much in our attire is meerly
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:20720:21"/>
accidentall; for, <hi>Potest adeſſe &amp; abeſſe.</hi> It may bee allowed, and in truth it might aſwell bee ſpared. But they came yet nearer him; and ſtript him of his Coate; neither did they take from him a part of his Coat,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 10.</note> as <hi>Hanun</hi> tooke <hi>Dauids</hi> Embaſſadors, and cut off their coates at the waſte. He that takes ſome and leaues ſome is counted now an honeſt Thiefe: but <hi>they ſtript him of his Coate, euen of his whole Coate,</hi> yea the Iewes thinke they ſtript him ſtarke naked, and ſo made him at vnawares a fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure of Chriſt vpon the Croſſe. But the firſt Coates that euer our firſt Parents vſed, were made of the skinnes of dead beaſts,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.</note> 
               <hi>Gen.</hi> 3. as it were a new skin put on; that couetous and cruell men might thinke that when they driue men to ſuch pouertie, as either to ſell their coate, or not to bee able to buy themſelues coats, they are as butcher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, as hee that taketh a knife, and flayeth off the skinne.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 22.</note>Therefore in the Law, it was not lawfull to take euery mans coate, no not to pledge, <hi>Deut.</hi> 22. They might not take the widdowes garment. And,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 22.</note> 
               <hi>Exod.</hi> 22. <hi>when they tooke any mans coate to pledge, they had it for a very ſhort Iubile,</hi> for it was to come home againe at night. And as <hi>Dorcas</hi> was commended for the coats which ſhee gaue, <hi>Act.</hi> 9. ſee <hi>Matth.</hi> 25.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 9.</note> many ſhall bee condemned for not cloathing the naked. Now as Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith, <hi>If hee ſhall goe to hell which giueth not his owne, whether thinke you ſhall he goe that taketh a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:20720:21"/>
another mans?</hi> But alas, what meant theſe men to doe with <hi>Ioſephs</hi> coate? <hi>Ioſephs</hi> coate was a ſmall bootie among them all: yea <hi>Ioſeph</hi> being the youngeſt of them all, his coate was too little for the leaſt of them all. Yet if <hi>Ioſeph</hi> had pilfered a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way old <hi>Reubens</hi> coate, euery man can tell how to cut ſhort and to make a large thing leſſe; but vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe it be in lying, wee haue little power to make things greater, Yet when <hi>Reuben</hi> getteth his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Leuies</hi> coate, it is as when a great rich man getteth the ſpoile of a Biſhoprick, which prankes vp his wife, paints out his children, multiplies his traine, magnifies his eſtate, and ſerueth him to many good purpoſes. But when <hi>Reuben</hi> takes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way little <hi>Ioſephs</hi> coate, it is as when a great man beggeth a little office, or hee who hath hundreds and thouſands of his owne, yet ſeeketh to impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priate or ſtrip a poore Parſonage, which when he hath, it will hardly ſerue him in with ſawce to his meate. And let vs here in a ſhaddow learne, neuer to lay hands on the coate which cannot profit vs. It is a point of high importance to hate all ſinne like a Serpent, yea though it promiſe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 4.</note> as the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill did to Chriſt, <hi>Omnia regna mundi.</hi> But there bee ſome ſinnes, which yeeld no man preſent pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit, yea nothing but repentance and ſhame,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.</note> that a man may ſay of them as Saint <hi>Paul, What profite haue wee of thoſe things whereof we are now aſhamed.</hi> Such a ſinne as Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> reports of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in his youth, <hi>Perreximus nocte intempeſta ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſsimi
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:20720:22"/>
adoleſcentuli, &amp;c. A ſort of wilde and wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton Youths, were agreed to goe out and to robbe a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine Apple-tree, and in ſuch a night, as a man would not haue turned a Dog out of doores, and for ſuch an Apple as when they had it, they threw it out of doores.</hi> Now ſaith hee; What meant I <hi>vt eſſem gratis ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus, to bee ſo wicked for nothing.</hi> A good leſſon for Gallants, and young Gentlemen, who doe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny things in their liues, of a wantonneſſe and bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery, which ſinne, and ſinne, and reape by their ſinne no profit but ſinne.<note place="margin">1. <hi>Reg.</hi> 21.</note> Such men are worſe then <hi>Ahab,</hi> for <hi>Ahab</hi> yet ſold himſelfe to worke wickedneſſe. Now hee that ſelleth himſelfe hath ſomewhat for himſelfe; but he that ſinneth wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonly, giueth himſelfe to the Diuell for nothing, and he is ſo much the more accomptable to GOD, by how much hee was content, for no prouocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to forſake GOD.</p>
            <p>But though <hi>Ioſephs</hi> coate did not ſerue his Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren to weare, yet they had a vſe for it, that ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it to <hi>Iacob</hi> dipped in blood, they might hide their ſinne by it, ſo that as <hi>Eraſmus</hi> ſaid ſometime of a Friers Cowle, that it was like Charitie, <hi>Quia operit multitudinem peccatorum, Becauſe it hid a world of wickedneſſe:</hi> ſo wee may ſay of <hi>Ioſephs</hi> coate, that the out-ſide of an honeſt man, doth oft-times hide a multitude of ſinne; for all the care is now to ſinne with a couer, and then to ſeeme honeſt, and, <hi>Si non caſte, tamen caute,</hi> The rule of <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh</hi> chaſtitie, is diſperſed into euery veyne, and
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:20720:22"/>
part of life, and ſo <hi>Iacob</hi> ſee it not, wee care not what we doe.</p>
            <p>But <hi>Ioſephs</hi> coate is here marked with a diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, <hi>They ſtript him out of his Coate.</hi> Which Coate? For it may be <hi>Ioſeph</hi> had two coates vpon one body, as wee many times haue two faces vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der one hood. Therefore it is anſwered, <hi>His par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty-coloured Coate.</hi> Now that which wee call a party-coloured, ſome call a ſide-coate, or a coate with ſleeues, ſome a painted, ſome an embroide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, ſome a ſilken coate: ſome call it a coate of many threads, ſome a coate of many pieces, but the moſt (and ſo let it goe) a coate of many co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours. If any man will coniecture what <hi>Iacob</hi> ſhould meane to make his ſonne ſuch a coate, firſt, I anſwere, that <hi>Iacob</hi> was much beholden to the party-coloured. For when vpon the compoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on betwixt Him and <hi>Laban,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Geneſ.</hi> 30.</note> the party-coloured fell to his ſhare, it was his inriching, and yet I yeeld not this for a reaſon. Neither would I haue our maſters of the Law to thinke, that <hi>Ioſephs</hi> pyed coate was a ſeruants Liuerie, for hee that could frame to dwell in a Tent, to keepe ſheepe, and to put vp wrongs for Religions ſake, he little needed to bring vp any of his ſonnes to the Law. The Law came not in till men grew more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentious, and vnruly minded. Neither did <hi>Iacob</hi> make this gay coate of a fond and wanton loue, as the manner of many is, to paint out their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren like Puppits, and their daughters like Idols,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:20720:23"/>
as if they meant to worſhip them; firſt to adorne, and then to adore them.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 25.</note> For <hi>Iacob</hi> is defined to be a plaine man, one that asked no more but for his neceſſitie, meate and cloathing. Therefore ſome thinke that this coate was a Prieſtly gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, wherewith <hi>Iacob</hi> meant to inveſt <hi>Ioſeph</hi> by reaſon of his birth-right. For in thoſe dayes till the Prieſthood was otherwiſe diſpoſed of, the el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſonne was ſtil a Prieſt to the familie, though in theſe dayes, the elder ſonne of a right bad Squire would thinke it foule ſcorne to be a Prieſt, yea a Prelate to a whole Countrie. And though <hi>Ioſeph</hi> were the youngeſt but one, yet the birth-right was his, as it is ſaid, 1. <hi>Chron.</hi> 5. For <hi>Iacob</hi> had three Heires, one a naturall Heire, which was <hi>Reuben,</hi> who loſt it by default; another an Heire ſpirituall, which was <hi>Iudah,</hi> of whom came <hi>Chriſt;</hi> and a third, an Heire actuall, which was <hi>Ioſeph.</hi> Some againe thinke, that <hi>Iacob</hi> made to <hi>Ioſeph</hi> this coate of many colours, for the aboundance and varietie of Grace and Vertue in him. For whereas it is ſaid, <hi>Verſ.</hi> 3. that <hi>Iacob</hi> loued <hi>Ioſeph</hi> beſt, becauſe he begate him in his old age, yet for ſo much as he begate a later ſonne, whom hee yet loued leſſe, ſome therefore carrie that ſaying after the Hebrew phraſe thus, that <hi>Iacob</hi> loued <hi>Ioſeph</hi> beſt, becauſe hee was to him the ſonne of old age, that though younger in yeeres, yet grauer and ancienter in vertue. And why might not <hi>Ioſeph</hi> for his vertue be called the eldeſt, though in yeeres
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:20720:23"/>
a child, as <hi>Rehoboam</hi> for his folly is called a child, euen when he was fortie yeeres old, 2. <hi>Chron.</hi> 13.<note place="margin">2. <hi>Chron.</hi> 13.</note> And indeed the beſt ground of the Parents loue, is the feare of God, and the ſeede of vertue in their children; which of <hi>Ioſephs</hi> vertue began euen then to ſprowt, and after did ſo flouriſh, as the earth neuer bare ſo excellent a flower. <hi>He was wiſe, Pharaoh</hi> ſaid, <hi>there was none in the Kingdome like him.</hi> Gen. 41. Hee was ſo faithfull, as being in priſon himſelfe, yet was made Keeper of the priſon, and kept that which kept him, <hi>Geneſ.</hi> 39. He was chaſte, euen in the aſſault of a ſtrong tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptation, as hee loſt his coate to keepe his honeſtie, whereas many now fell their coates to looſe their honeſtie. How gentle, kinde, and louing to his father hee was, looke <hi>Gen.</hi> 45. and there you ſhall ſee by the Corne which hee ſent in the famine to feede him, and by the Chariots which afterward hee ſent to fetch him. And that which of all is a vertue rare in theſe dayes, hee was able to ſay, <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitte, ſicut remittimus.</hi> For the offence which his brethren here made him, hee freely forgaue it, and wept when they ſpake of it, <hi>Gen.</hi> 50. So that <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſephs</hi> coate of many colours was nothing but the ſigne of his many vertues, to ſhew how <hi>Iacob</hi> ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured vertue in his children.</p>
            <p>Therefore, here I thinke began Heraldrie and the honour of Armes. For when the people, at the firſt being equall in degree, grew in admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of them whom they ſaw to excell in vertue,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:20720:24"/>
they practiſed by Ceremonies and ſenſible Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to adorne them. The holy Ghoſt in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture oftentimes applying the ſame kindes of orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and honour. For in Scripture Gold ſignifies holineſſe or zeale to GOD, the excellency of ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue. And Siluer ſignifies the pureneſſe of Charitie, and Loue to one another,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cant.</hi> 1.10.</note> which GOD intended when hee promiſed his Church to make her bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of Gold with waues of Siluer. <hi>Cant.</hi> 1.10. In the Scripture,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 26.14.</note> 
               <hi>the Iewiſh Tabernacle, was couered or mantled with red.</hi> Exod. 26.14. Which reports vnto the hearer boldneſſe and defence vnto death, to ſignifie that they would protect the Sanctuary, Religion, and the Law, euen to the effuſion of their laſt blood. In the Scripture, Greene ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ſignifieth Fruitfulneſſe in good workes, for which cauſe Chriſt is called, <hi>a greene Tree.</hi> Luk. 23.31. and ſometime it ſignifieth Flouriſhing in the protection of GOD,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jerem.</hi> 15.8.</note> for, <hi>hee that truſteth in God, his leafe it ſaid to bee euer Greene.</hi> Ierem. 15.8. In the Scripture, Blacke ſignifieth Conſtant, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mutable, and therefore among the praiſes of CHRIST,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cant.</hi> 5.11.</note> 
               <hi>his head is ſaid to bee curled and blacke as a Rauen.</hi> Cant. 5.11. In the Scripture, <hi>the Saints are ſaid to bee cloathed in White.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Reuel.</hi> 19.4.</note> Reuel. 19.4. which <hi>Verſ.</hi> 8. is expounded to bee, <hi>the righteouſneſſe of the Saints:</hi> yet not righteouſneſſe inherent, but by imputation in Chriſt.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Reuel.</hi> 7.14.</note> For, <hi>Reu.</hi> 7.14. <hi>They waſht their long Roabes and made them white in the blood of the Lambe.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Reuel.</hi> 19.16.</note> And therefore, as <hi>Reuel.</hi> 19.16.
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:20720:24"/>
               <hi>Christ had his name written vpon his Coate,</hi> ſo theſe vertues were doubtleſſe written in the many co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours of <hi>Ioſephs</hi> Coate.</p>
            <p>Therefore Gentle-women, Good-women, and Siſters in CHRIST, heere is no warrant for Wantonneſſe and Superfluitie. A little Scripture God wot ſerues to inlarge your libertie, and ſhee who can ſcarce put on her Coate, yet can readily conclude from <hi>Ioſephs</hi> Coate, If hee then, why not wee? If Men may be ſo fine, much more may Women. And indeed, it holdeth oftentimes too ſtrongly, for many plaine men are oftentimes brought to hang all their owne pride, and their wealth, and their wits too, on their Wiues backes. But what if <hi>Ioſeph</hi> ware a Coate of many colours, therefore, yee may doe ſo too. It is true, if it ſtands with your eſtates, perhaps you may. For <hi>Dauids</hi> Daughter ware a Coate of many colours,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 13.</note> which is warranted by Cuſtome of the time and reſpect of her place. And CHRIST ſpake it without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach, when hee ſaid, <hi>They that weare ſoft ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment are in Kings houſes.</hi> Math. 11.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 11.</note> So as yee may doe any thing, yet be proud of nothing. Yee may by <hi>Ioſephs</hi> example paint out your Coates, but take heed of painting your Faces; yee may by <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſephs</hi> example weare many Colours, not too ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Fancies, not euery Moone to mint a new faſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Women ſure were made in Gods image as well as Men, now of GOD it is ſaid, <hi>That there is with him no variableneſſe nor ſhadow of Change.</hi> Iam.
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:20720:25"/>
1.17. Finally, miſtake not the matter, <hi>Ioſephs</hi> Coate, was a coate of Armes, the outward enſigne of his inward Vertues, and if yee ſhew more co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours without then vertues within, then are yee like the Foxe, your Skinne, your Coate is worth more then your Bodies.</p>
            <p>Againe, heere is a leſſon for men, eſpecially for Courtiers, a leſſon worth the learning. For what was the ground of all this griefe, but that the painted Coate muſt bee put on <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> on <hi>Ioſeph</hi> I ſay, and of none of the Elder brethren. For, <hi>Luk.</hi> 15 The Elder brother will not looke into the houſe, if but a Calfe be killed for the Younger, and men haue no patience to indure it, if but an Office be tranſlated, or any Honour beſtowed where they like not. O but giue <hi>Iacob</hi> leaue to giue the partie coloured Coate, binde not the hands of a Prince, for when Subiects aſſume to limit the Prince, then they preſume to bee aboue the Prince. And looke what ſinnes are managed in Preſumption, they end for the moſt part in confuſion.</p>
            <p>Againe, heere is for You (moſt Excellent) here is for You, a mirrour of your ſelfe, and this Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall Kingdome. Your Maieſtie is to vs as <hi>Iacob,</hi> who hath wreſtled with GOD, and obtayned a Kingly Bleſſing: and wee are to your Maieſtie as <hi>Ioſeph</hi> and his Brethren, a multitude of Sonnes, begotten of diuers Mothers, ſome diſtinguiſhed by Religion, ſome by Condition, ſome by Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, ſome by Countrey ornation. Some of vs are
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:20720:25"/>
diſtinguiſhed by Religion, for the Sonnes of <hi>Leah</hi> come in from <hi>Rome,</hi> and tell your Maieſtie they are of the Elder houſe, and therefore no reaſon our Sheafe ſhould ſtand and theirs ſhould fall. But <hi>Leah</hi> their Mother was bleare-eyed, and they in truth are blinde, in a falſe admiration of their owne Antiquitie. For what though <hi>Leah</hi> crept firſt into <hi>Iacobs</hi> bed, yet <hi>Ioſephs</hi> Mother was firſt betroathed, and therefore as it is in the Embleme, <hi>Tandem ſuum iuſtitia obtinuit.</hi> And <hi>Ioſeph</hi> had the Birth-right, therefore to your Maieſtie comes <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph</hi> for preheminence, that our CHVRCH may ſtand and theirs may fall. Sometime againe, wee are diſtinguiſhed by State or Condition, for ſome of vs bee rich, and ſome of vs be poore, and as the Poore for the moſt part maligne and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fame the rich, ſo the Rich oppreſſe and deuoure the poore, Therefore to your Maieſtie comes the Rich, that they may keepe their Colours, and to your Maieſtie comes the Poore, that they may keepe their Coates vpon their backes. Sometime againe, wee are diſtinguiſhed by Profeſſion, ſome holding of the Laietie, and ſome of <hi>Leui,</hi> that is, the Church or Clergie. <hi>Ioſephs</hi> Brethren tooke from him a partie coloured Coate, but many of our Brethren would giue to vs a partie coloured Coat, that wee ſhould weare as much Blew as Blacke, and liue like <hi>Micha's</hi> Leuite, by Liuery ſeruice, and attending. Therefore to your Maieſtie comes the Laietie, that <hi>Leui</hi> may doe his Dutie, and to
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:20720:26"/>
your Maieſtie comes <hi>Leui</hi> that hee may haue his Dutie. Sometime againe, wee are diuided by Countrey or Nation, for hee is in <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and he is in <hi>Scottiſh,</hi> and I know not what, and GOD knowes a little thing ſerues to make a rupture, and to diſturbe this turbulent braine of ours. Therefore as your Maieſtie is Lord of all, ſo come wee to your Maieſtie to vnite vs all, and as you Crowned vs with one Name, ſo procure vnto vs one heart and minde, preſerue vs from ſtrife, and if it may bee from ſecret Emulation, for Hate ſeekes blood, and Blood ſeekes blood againe. It is no maruaile though theſe men ſought to kill their Brother, for their hands were lately embrewed in the <hi>Sichemites</hi> blood, and as the Tragedian ſaith, <hi>Creſcit dum non punitur ſcelus.</hi> Hee that is pardo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned for killing of a Stranger, will aſſay at the next blow to kill his Brother, the next thought will be to kill his owne Father. And to whom doth Blood now cry for Protection? Indeed, when there was no King the blood of <hi>Abel</hi> cryed im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediatly vnto GOD, but your Maieſtie being King, it cryeth now to you, becauſe you are in ſtead of God.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, heere is for all men, to ſee in <hi>Ioſeph</hi> an I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of this vaine and inconſtant World. Hee that was the day before betweene his Fathers knees, is now in his bloody Brothers hands, and he who euen now was in a painted Coate, is now ſtarke naked and without a Coate. It was wont
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:20720:26"/>
to be ſaid for a ſure Prouerbe, <hi>As ſure as the Coate on your backe;</hi> as ſure indeed, for wee are ſure of nothing. For what aſſurance haue wee, when our Father puts on, and our Brethren pull off, when one man beſtowes it, and ten men are ready to take it away. And thus it is with your Coat, your Riches, and your Treaſures, yea thus it is with your partie coloured Coate, your Titles and your Honours. The world is like <hi>Nabuchadonozer</hi> his Image, Gold in the head, Siluer in the breſt, Braſſe in the belly, Iron in the legges, but the feet, which ſhould bee ſtrongeſt are of Clay and Earth, and this Golden glory hath no ſtrength to ſtand vpon.</p>
            <p>Yet let no man be diſcouraged; for as our good oft ends in euill, ſo our euill oft ends in good a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine. <hi>Ioſeph</hi> is heere ſtript, anon hee is ſold, after that impriſoned, but after all that hee is exalted,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Geneſ.</hi> 30.</note> and made the great Commander of <hi>Aegypt,</hi> that a man may truely ſay. His fortune was of as many colours as his Coate. Yea, twice now hath <hi>Ioſeph</hi> loſt his Coate, once heere in the hands of his Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, and againe by the hands of that Harlot <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>typhars</hi> wife. But afterward <hi>Pharaoh</hi> doeth inueſt him with a Ring and a Chaine, and a royall Coat.</p>
            <p>And thus by euill and good, by chance and change lyeth the way to Heauen, whereas wee murmur but at one affliction, and grudge if wee haue not Heauen for nothing. But there bee but two wayes, if wee be vpon the broad way, that is,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:20720:27"/>
If we haue all things at will, and nothing to trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble vs, wee may ſuſpect we are not right, there is nothing ſo fearefull as to bee Fortunate. But if we be vpon the narrow way, if pinched and pricked with Thornes, if ſpoyled, oppreſſed, defrauded, defamed, theſe things may import a better paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage, that they will land vs at the end in the gates of Heauen. Vnto which hee bring vs, that hath ſo dearely bought vs, IESVS CHRIST the righteous, to whom with the Father and the Holy Ghoſt, bee all Praiſe and Glory, Power and Dominion, now and for euer, AMEN.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:20720:27"/>
            <head>A Friend of the Publiſher here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of to the Readers.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>READERS,</hi> If any of you liſt to bee ſo cenſori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous (in this criticall Age) as to cenſure the late Publiſhing of this praecedent <hi>Sermon;</hi> Giue me leaue to anſwer you, that <hi>It</hi> being the <hi>Poſthu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me-manes</hi> of a Reuerend Learned and Eloquent Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine, deceaſed; was doubtleſſe reſerued not without ſome Diuine Prouidence till now: the Subiect being ſo ſeaſonable for the occaſion: And the Publiſher hereof, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> reuerend friend, certes, his ingenuitie, in my iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, deſerueth gratefull acceptance at the least, in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyning his elaborate Conſolatorie Epiſtle or Preface to that <hi>Worthy Societie,</hi> with the ſaid <hi>Sermon:</hi> there being ſo neere affinitie betweene <hi>IOSEPHS</hi> vnnaturall Perſecutions in <hi>Aegypt</hi> by his <hi>Brethren,</hi> and the inhumane Tortures of our Countrey-men in <hi>Amboyna,</hi> by the either Atheiſticall or Arminian <hi>Dutch</hi> There: The true Relation whereof I profeſſe I could nor can read but with teares, nor thinke on without ſorrow of heart. And as <hi>Ioſephs</hi> Perſecutions cryed vp to God till they were auenged, ſo without doubt doth the <hi>Blood</hi> of our miſerably macerated and maſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Countrey-men crie at Heauen Gates for Venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance: For <hi>GOD</hi> is Iuſt, and whoſe is Vengeance but His? What ſhould I ſay more, in the Argument? there being ſo much, ſo learnedly, ſo piouſly, ſo iudiciouſly ſaid in the Premiſſes: which I trowe no Reader that hath either. Learning or Iudgement will denie. So farewell, <hi>&amp; fruere.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>H. D.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
